<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in August the 13. 1610. In Canterbury to the corporation of black-smiths Declaring the goodnesse, necessity, antiquity and vse of that trade which workes in iron. With directions to men of this, and of all other trades and callings, how to carry themselues religiously and iustly therein. Whereunto are annexed a short catechisme, with two short tables. The first opening the parts of wisedome, to be learned from mans mortality, out of Psa.90.12. The latter laying forth the order of Gods counsell, touching the saluation of the elect, out of Rom.8.29.30. By Thomas Wilson preacher.</title>
            <author>Wilson, Thomas, 1563-1622.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15528</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25797</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104831</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840562</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840562</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5078</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15528)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5078)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 863:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in August the 13. 1610. In Canterbury to the corporation of black-smiths Declaring the goodnesse, necessity, antiquity and vse of that trade which workes in iron. With directions to men of this, and of all other trades and callings, how to carry themselues religiously and iustly therein. Whereunto are annexed a short catechisme, with two short tables. The first opening the parts of wisedome, to be learned from mans mortality, out of Psa.90.12. The latter laying forth the order of Gods counsell, touching the saluation of the elect, out of Rom.8.29.30. By Thomas Wilson preacher.</title>
                  <author>Wilson, Thomas, 1563-1622.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by N. Okes] for Simon Waterson, dwelling in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Crowne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached before the corporation of black-smiths.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; print show-through; the copy catalogued contains sermon only.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5078:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5078:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED IN AVGVST THE 13. 1610. In Canterbury to the Corporation of Black-ſmiths.</p>
            <p>Declaring the goodneſſe, neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, antiquity and vſe of that Trade which workes in Iron. With directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to men of this, and of all other trades and callings, how to carry themſelues religiouſly and iuſtly therein.</p>
            <p>Whereunto are annexed a ſhort Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme, with two ſhort Tables. The firſt opening the parts of wiſedome, to be learned from mans mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, out of <hi>Pſa.</hi> 90.12.</p>
            <p>The latter laying forth the order of Gods Counſell, touching the ſaluation of the elect, out of Rom. 8.29.30.</p>
            <p>By THOMAS WILSON Preacher.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Simon Waterſon,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard at the ſigne of the Crowne. 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5078:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5078:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL, MAI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>TER DOCTOR SMITH, Maiſter of Clare Hall in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, health in our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et it not offend you that I your ſonne ſo farre in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior to you in grauity, &amp; ſufficiency of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, haue thus preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to followe you in be ſame ſteppes, I meane, preaching vpon be ſame Text, and publiſhing this my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ude worke. I haue done nothing (neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould I if I would) vnto your diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I do but liſpe, where you ſpeake; I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reepe where you did go, and runne: I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed
<pb facs="tcp:5078:3"/>the low ſhrubs, you the high and mightie Cedars. I the ſubiect, you the King, Prince, Councell, and Nobles of the Land. You in a loftie, I in a low ſtyle. I ſpake to a fewe Mechanichans, you to a mightie Monarche, and many worthy Peeres. Your labours preferred to publick view by motion of a moſt reuerent Father. Dedicated primarily to a moſt learned and excellent King; and ſecondarily, to a great and noble Counſellor. I alas do looke no higher then to your worſhipfull ſelfe (and haue need of pardon for this preſumption to) being moued to ſhew my ſelfe by ſome priuate perſons, who deſired this birth ſhould not die in the birth: But happily you will be offended that I call you father, hauing no reſemblance and likeneſſe to you, not ſo much as in countenance, gate, ſpeech or Iesture. True it is, I reſemble you in nothing at all; neither in wit, nor clocution, learning, experience, reading, iudgement: I haue no agreement nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence with you in method, inſtruction,
<pb facs="tcp:5078:3"/>diſpoſition, application, phraſe, example or ſentence, ſcarce a word from you (for I had ſeene you foure yeares ago, and had not ſince lookt on you.) Howbeit I am bold, and I trust (without blame) to entitle you Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; becauſe of your precedency in years, grauitie, graces, experience, degree and place, as alſo for that you not onely went before me in time, I being an after birth: but were the occaſion of this birth, in ſo much as when I was to chuſe a Text wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to preach before a Corporation of Smiths; your entreating on this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture before me moued, and brought me the ſooner to thinke, and reſolue of it as meete, and fit for my purpoſe. If it ſhall pleaſe you not to diſdaine me, I will bind my ſelfe not to enuie you. Your labours may obſcure mine, but my light cannot dimme yours, it ſhines too bright: yet Bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers skinnes helped the building of the Tabernacle, as well as ſilke and purple. So as Gods children profit, and his glory be promoted by the varietie of our gifts, and
<pb facs="tcp:5078:4"/>endeauors, that ſhall ſuffice me plentifully and I doubt not, but it will content you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Fare you well.</salute> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>October. <hi>25. 1610.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>THOMAS WILSON, One of the ſixe Preachers in Canterbury Church.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5078:4"/>
            <head>A Sermon Preached in Canterbury to the Corporation of Blacke-ſmiths, declaring the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, neceſſity, antiquity, and vſe of that trade which workes in Iron.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. SAM. 13.19.20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>There was not a Smith found throughout all the land of Iſrael, for the Philistines ſaid, leaſt the Hebrewes make them ſwords or ſpeares.</p>
                  <p>VVherefore all the Iſraelites went downe to the Philiſtines, to ſharpen euery man his mattocke, his ſhare, his axe, and his weeding hooke.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T plainely appeareth by ſacred Story,
<note place="margin">Summe of the text.</note> that God had deliuered the Iſraelites into the hands of the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines, who were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5078:5"/>their Lords, and exerciſed do minion ouer them. Now in this tex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it is ſhewed in few termes what art, &amp; deuiſe the Philiſtines did ſtill vſe to keepe the necke of the Iſraelites in their yoke: namely this, by ſpoyling them of all armour, and depriuing them of all meanes how to come by any weapons: for they rooted out of their land, both out of villages, and citties all the Black-ſmiths.</p>
            <p>The text is hiſtoricall,
<note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> and contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth three parts.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, is the narration of a want, or an euill hapned: which is ſet forth by the perſons, to whom: to wit, the Iſraelites or Hebrewes (in the land of Iſrael;) ſecondly, bv the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of the iudgement <hi>(in all the land not a Smith found.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other part of our text is,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> a confirmation, rendring a reaſon of the want, or iudgement, and it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the inſtrumentall cauſe, to wit, the Philiſtines who were the meanes and inſtruments of this great
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5078:5"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ill <hi>(for the Philiſtines ſaid.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third and laſt part is, a notation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d deſignement of the effects which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llowed this euill brought vpon Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l, by the crafty counſell of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſtines. Theſe effects concerne the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e both of warre <hi>(leſt the Hebrewes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake them ſwords or ſpeares)</hi> and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eace <hi>(all the Iſraelites went downe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Philiſtines to ſharpen euery man his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>are, &amp;c.</hi> Now let vs proceed to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>terpretation of the words, that we may raiſe vp doctrines out of them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd make vſe of them for your edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There was no Smith.]</hi>
               <note place="margin">Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> There be Smiths) of ſundry kindes and ſorts, according to the diuerſity of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect wherein they worke; there be that worke in gold, in copper, in ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, whence we haue Goldſmiths, Siluer-ſmiths, as <hi>Demetrius Asts</hi> 10.24. Alſo Copper-ſmiths 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. but the circumſtances do very clearly proue, that our text ſpeaketh of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5078:6"/>Black-ſmiths, and ſuch as worke i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yron; for theſe make ſwords and ſpeares,
<note place="margin">Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Dignity of this trade.</note> and by the hand of theſe ſhares, mattocks, and axes be both framed and ſharpened. Now in that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pleaſeth the holy Ghoſt to take know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this trade or myſtery,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> and to name it with fauour and liking (as he doth) Hence I gather the goodneſſe, worth, and dignity of the ſame, that it is a trade alowable and noble; for it is no ſmall ennobling and dignifying of any perſon or thing,
<note place="margin">Lanàari à laudato non minima laus.</note> (if we rightly iudge of it) to be named in the moſt ſacred Scriptures by the Spirit of God with approbation. If it be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a matter of grace, counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and credit to be mentioned with reſpect and commendation in a prophane ſtory; how much more grace doth it bring to a function or perſon to be honored ſo farre as with good alowance to be written and ſet downe in holy writ.</p>
            <p>I haue certainely heard of a weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5078:6"/>Citizen in London, who hauing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> priuy Seale ſent him from our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>te famous Queene, tooke it to be no ſmall fauour done vnto him. Doth the Queene (ſaith he) know me, ſhe ſhall lacke no money, if I haue it; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd may not our Black-ſmiths, then account it a fauour and honour vnto him, that the King of heauen takes knowledge of him, and hath put his name, and memory (not in a peece of paper) but in the booke of bookes? eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, ſeeing ſundry other vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of greater worth and value, in the eyes of the world are paſt by of him, without the leaſt touch or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? To be ſhort, do men of meane ſort thinke it to be a credit vnto them if but a noble man do name them, and ſpeake of them with loue and reſpect; may not I then iuſtly affirme, and ſpeake it to be a dignity to this meane trade (as men account it) that the Lord of Lords hath from his owne moſt holy mouth honored: yea, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5078:7"/>it by a louing fauourable mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it?</p>
            <p>Let the knowledge and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereof ſerue for theſe purpoſes and vſes.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſes. </seg>
               </label>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, to ſtir vp your hearts to giue thanks to God for placing and ſetting you in ſuch a calling, as hath giuen vnto it both warrant, and worth from his owne mouth.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to pray vnto him for his grace, that you may walke in it with all good conſcience, that as your trade is good and honeſt, ſo you may deale in it wel and honeſtly, gaining credit to that vocations, vpon which it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to put ſuch credit, and honouring him who hath honored you.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, let this prouoke you to performe, and go through the hard labours of this calling with a more willing and chearefull heart, doing your tough worke not grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gingly, or of neceſſity, but with a ready minde; for that God that hath honoured your calling, doth loue
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5078:7"/>chearefull workers. Laſtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> let it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh others that are wont to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſe your perſons for the baſeneſſe of your trade, hereafter learne for your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rades ſake to make better account of your ſelues; for if no trade be baſe in it ſelfe, being Gods ordinnace, much leſſe is that, which hath Gods commendation. And thus much be ſpoken of the dignity and worth of your trade.</p>
            <p>In the next place,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> let vs obſerue the antiquity thereof,
<note place="margin">Antiquity.</note> in that it hath bene vſed in the world, not for a few years, it is no ſtart vp, and newly diuiſed trade (as it were a yeſter-daies bird) but it was bred and borne long ſince, &amp; hath had ſo many hundred of years gone ouer his head, as it hath now gotten not onely gray, but white haires, euen as white as wool, or ſnow. It is ſixteene hundred yeares, and more, ſince the incarnation of Chriſt, who was borne in the yeare of the world 3928. Howbeit, your trade
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5078:8"/>was liuing, and flouriſhing to, a great while before this time: euen in the daies when <hi>Samuel,</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Iſrael, which was 490 yeares from the worlds creation (as the learned affirme:) nay, which is more, we find, in the hiſtory of Geneſis, that <hi>Tubal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4.22.</note> the ſeuenth from <hi>Adam,</hi> was the Father and Author of thoſe that worke in yron, and in braſſe: ſo as your trade is very ancient, which doth adde no ſmall increaſe of credit, and grace vnto it. For antiquity (when it is ioyned with goodneſſe) doth more augment the eſteeme, and regard of a good thing. We are commanded (ye know) to <hi>honour the gray head, and to riſe before the perſon of an old man.</hi> Leui. 19.32. It is written alſo, that <hi>old age when it is found in the way of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, it is a crowne of glory to a man.</hi> Prou. 16.31. As ancientneſſe breeds reuerence to perſons, ſo it doth to things when they be good and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, wicked men the elder
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5078:8"/>they be, the more to be deteſted; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ertuous men, the more aged they be, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the more to be reſpected; for euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir age is a crowne to them, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hemſelues be righteous. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er it fareth with things, which if they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e euill they are the worſe they more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncient they be (for antiquity is a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arce to naughtineſſe) but if they be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood,
<note place="margin">Conſuetudo ſine veritat eſtv tus error.</note> they be the better by being ancient: for antiquity doth put more grace vpon a good thing, and makes it venerable. And were it not ſo that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here were ſome moment in priority of time, as well as of place, our two Vniuerſities ſhould deſerue ſome blame, which haue ſtriuen ſo long both by word and writing which ſhould be more ancient. In a word, ſeeing it is written that old wine is better then new, and a new friend is leſſe to be eſteemed then an old (as experience teacheth (it is therefore ſure that the oldneſſe, and long continuance of any good calling
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5078:9"/>ſhould make it to be more acceptabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and gracious.</p>
            <p>The which point beeing we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> weighed of you,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> it ſhould ſerue as a ſecond ſpurre to quicken you to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake, and performe the labour o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your vocation with ſo much the more willingneſſe, diligence, and vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rightneſſe. Many euill men do ſticke vnto, and with greedineſſe follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſundry euil things, vnder pretence of cuſtome; becauſe they haue bene long vſed (as if preſcription could iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie vices, as it doth mens titles and things euill at the firſt, could in time become good by long vſage of them) which to thinke, were a great madnes; yet many men (as if they had a deſire to be mad, and to dote with reaſon) would therefore be excuſed for their embracing euill things and courſes; becauſe they haue bene accuſtomed to be done of old, and much frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; with how much better reaſon may good men cleaue to good things,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5078:9"/>and exerciſe good trades when goodneſſe is commended by reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent antiquity?</p>
            <p>Let vs now paſſe forward to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the neceſſity of your function,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <note place="margin">Neceſſity.</note> which appeares in this, that when the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nd of Iſrael wanted it, the people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here had a ſenſible, and great miſſe of it, neither ſhould it be ſpoken of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ere as a iudgement to want Smiths, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the hauing of them were not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. Reaſon and experience teach, that good men, good creatures, good ordinances, good vocations are neuer ſo well perceiued how good and needfull they be by enioying and hauing them, as by wanting and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going them.
<note place="margin">Caren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magis quam fruendo. Virtutem preſentem odimus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas ſublatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; ex otulis quaerium in vidi.</note> This is a corruption in mans nature leſſe to eſteeme and care for good things which be preſent, then for thoſe which be abſent; the reaſon is, becauſe the want doth more bewray the neceſſity and vſe. The exceeding and continuall lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation for the death of <hi>Ioſiah</hi> (that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5078:10"/>good king) doth tel vs how much they miſſed him being gone, who beeing preſent they did not ſo regard. <hi>Lam.</hi> 4. When our Sauiour tels his hearers that the time would come, when they ſhould deſire to ſee but one of the daies of the Sonne of man. He doth hereby inſinuate that the Meſiah be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent in perſon, was without due reſpect to him and his doctrine, and that the great need of him and his teaching would be more diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the abſence of them. The Sunne is a glorious creature very beautifull and benificial to the world, yet our daily beholding it doth leſſen our account of it, and our thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to God for it, were it taken from vs but one yeare, by the want of it we ſhould be forced to learne the great and manifold neceſſity of this one creature: What, do I ſpeake of the Sunne that moſt lightſome and goodly creature, if we ſhould lacke either the aire to breath in, or the fire,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5078:10"/>or water, or the earth, or trees, foules, or beaſts, or any one creature allotted of God to our neceſſities, though we had and enioyed all the reſt, yet the want of that very one would be felt, and would teach vs experimentally the neceſſity of that, and of all the reſt: and this which I ſpeake of the creatures, I would haue vnderſtood of the members of our body, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there is not the leſt, but is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; the foote, the loweſt and baſeſt member, yet it cannot be ſaid there is no need of it. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.21. This which is true in the naturall body, is verified alſo into the Eccleſiaſticall, and politicall body in the Church and common wealth. There is no Church-officer, or ordinance that can be ſpared: if we were without either preaching, or reading, or Sacraments, or prayer, we ſhould ſoone ſee that we could not be long without it, and be well, ſo truely is that which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſpoken, that God and nature
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5078:11"/>hath done nothing in vaine.
<note place="margin">Deus et na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura nihil ſeterunt fruſtra.</note> Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the common wealth, were it ſo with vs here in England, as it was ſometimes with Gods people in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, that there were no gouernour, or Magiſtrate in our land, as ſometime there was no King in Iſrael. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 18.1. The horrible confuſions, the excrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble impieties, and iniquities, that would abound in our ſtate, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow it, as a winter-floud would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force, euen thoſe which be moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient of authority, and moſt aduerſe to gouerment,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 8.5.</note> to cry out as that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple did, <hi>make vs now a king to iudge vs?</hi> Howſoeuer now that we haue the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of rule and rulers, we do not rightly value it: yet were there no ruler to be found in all our land, we ſhould quickly miſſe it: ſo auailable and effectuall is the abſence of a thing to teach vs the neceſſity of it. After Magiſtracy, conſider the ordinance of Matrimony, which howſoeuer by being common groweth contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5078:11"/>with many (as other things do) yet the lacke of it, would ſoone pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime &amp; ſpeake forth the neceſſity of it, in as much as without it,
<note place="margin">Matrimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umrei pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Eccleſiae ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> men e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gn coeleſtis ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narium.</note> the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen ſhould miſle many inhabitants, and the kingdoms of the earth ſhould in ſhort time haue none at all.</p>
            <p>And no maruaile that there is ſuch need of theſe maine ordinances, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is not the meaneſt manuary trade, or art, but when it is lacking the body politicke doth feele the miſſe of it with griefe, and ſmart, whereof we haue ſufficient proofe in this very text, which inſtructs vs to ſee that the whole land of Iſrael was the worſe for want of the Black-ſmiths, and ſure it could not otherwiſe be, for though the particular euils which came by this want, were not mentioned in our text (of the which we ſhall ſpeake more at large anon) yet common rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and ſence may teach vs the truth hereof. For of many trades which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5078:12"/>are now in this citty vſed, tell me which of them all you could lacke, or if you did lacke it, whether you ſhould not feele the want of it, and thinke it a great euill to be without it; yea though it were but your ſcauin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or chimney ſweeper.</p>
            <p>But if we ſhould looſe or be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either our Tailours, or Shooe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, or Smiths, Glouers, Ioyners, Carpenters, or any one of our mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt occupations, though we ſhould keepe all the reſt, yet thoſe that be of the beſt, and richeſt trades amongſt vs, ſhould eaſily ſee the great need of that one, and how hardly they could ſubſiſt without it. The mouſe may plucke a thorne out of the Lyons foote, which the Lyon could not do for himſelfe: ſo the baſeſt trades are neceſſary euen to the wealthieſt, and moſt worſhippifull Citizen, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are not in all things ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to themſelues,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Solus Deus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Gen. 17.2.</note> therefore can no more lacke the meaneſt tradeſmen,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5078:12"/>then the meaneſt artiſans can lacke them. For it fareth ſo with trades <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſciences, as it doth with linkes in a chaine, or ſteps in a ladder, whereof if one or two be wanting, the chaine is broken, and the ladder were of no vſe, for we could neither aſcend nor deſcend by it. Likewiſe there is ſuch a mutuall, and reciprocall neceſſity of trades in the common-wealth, that when any one faileth all the reſt are impaired. The comon-wealth is like vnto a kind and tender mother, which though ſhe be poore, and haue a great charge of children, yet would ſhe mourne for the loſſe of any one of them; ſo the land would mourne if is wanted but a Peuterer, or a Cutler, a needle-maker, or an yron mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p>But happily ſome will ſay,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſes. </seg>
               </label> to what purpoſe is it that you do thus enlarge the neceſſity of manuary trades and occupations?
<note place="margin">Of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of trades.</note> we do all know they are needfull for vs.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:5078:13"/>
            <p>It may be ſo, but there are many more that know this, then that do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſider it ſo, as to make a right vſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it. Let me therefore entreat you to thinke ſeriouſly vpon it, and bend your minds ſo to conſider it, as to make profit of it.</p>
            <p>And firſt of all,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſ. </seg>1</label> let it ſerue you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a rule to direct you to iudge of the warrant, ableneſſe and lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not only of this one trade o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Black-ſmiths, hut of all other ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary vocations amongſt vs. Your rule is this. Whatſoeuer calling is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the Church, Common-wealth or family: ſo as if it be wanting there will follow detriment or hurt, eithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to family, common-wealth or church This is a ſure argument that ſuch a calling is approueable before God and man in <hi>foro in ciuili, &amp; conſcientiae</hi> Hereby we do know that vermine are not Gods creatures, framed amongſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his workes of the ſixe dayes: becauſe were they all deſtroyed, yet the world
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5078:13"/>ſhould not want any thing of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. Alſo it is a certaine demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration that Carbuncles, Wennes, Warts, are no parts at all of the body: becauſe they being cut off and taken away, the body is not the worſe, but the better. Semblablewiſe, there needs no better reaſon to proue that common vſurers, which liue vpon the loane of money, eating other mens fleſh to cheriſh their owne, dice and card-makers, enterlude-makers, and players, fortune-tellers, &amp; palme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſters, coniecturall Mathematicall Aſtrologers, that by the Horoſcope aduenture to giue iudgement of the manners and euents of men, of their life and death. Alſo tapſters &amp; beere-drawers, Ballad-makers, pipers, and fidlers, beare-warders, and hobby-horſe-makers. Theſe, I ſay, and all ſuch like, which are ſo needleſſe and idle, that if none of them at all were found in all this land; yet not onely there would be no want of them, but
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5078:14"/>great cauſe to thanke God for the want of them (being properly and not by abuſe, as ale-houſes and brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers be, onely the neſts and nurceries to hatch &amp; harbor many foule vices) need no better euidence againſt them to conuince them to be ſuch as ought to be blotted out of the catalogue of warrantable trades; becauſe they be not onely needeleſſe, but ſome of them alſo vnprofitable and hurtfull: as on the other ſide it is an vngainſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able argument to proue any calling lawfull, if it may truly be ſaide it is needfull.
<note place="margin">Luk. 19.34.</note> 
               <hi>VVhen the owners of the colt</hi> (mentioned in the Goſpell) <hi>heard the Diſciples ſay the maiſter hath need of it, they let it go:</hi> Likewiſe, whatſoeuer trade or function it be vnto, which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church, or comon-wealth, or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily can ſay, I haue need of thee, we may very well and ſafely to that fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or calling giue a <hi>dimittimus,</hi> and <hi>quietus eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſide this rule to diſcerne of trades
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſ. </seg>2</label>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:5078:14"/>by, ye are to make a further vſe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ormer point, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this, both to repent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our ſelues with true and vnfained g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iefe of heart; becauſe yee haue not ſeene, or not eſteemed the goodneſſe of God in the benefit, and vſe of ſo many needfull trades as he hath affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you for commodity of life, but alſo inioyne it to your ſelfe as a law hereafter better to thinke vpon it, lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp your minds ſo high as hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, beholding and acknowledging the mercies of your louing Father, euen for the leſt of theſe mechanicall occupations.
<note place="margin">Quod cui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git cuiuis potest.</note> Otherwiſe for your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe that may befall you, that befell theſe Iſraelites, either wholly to want them, or enioy them without a bleſſing, putting the mony which you earne by them into a bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe bag.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt vſe is,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> in reſpect of you that are Magiſtrates (whereof I ſee ſome preſent this day) that as by vertue of your place and office, you
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5078:15"/>are the Fathers and Guardians of the common wealth in this place, put in truſt by God, and his Maieſtie, to ſee to the publicke weale of it:
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.2.3.</note> ſo it wold pleaſe you to make a conſcience of your duty herein, to afford your countenance and protection to all painefull tradeſmen, and vnto all needefull trades, the loweſt as well as the higheſt, not ſo cheriſhing ſome as you neglect the reſt, but equally maintaining, and ſupporting them al, all being equally behoofull, though all not equally excellent, and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>It is a good ſpeech of the heathen Oratour, that it is requiſite in a good gouernour ſo to reſpect one part of the weale-publicke, as that he doth not deſpiſe another. Hitherto I haue entreated of the firſt part of our text: to wit, the narration of the want, that Iſrael had of Smiths: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we haue ſeene the dignity, and the neceſſity of this vocation. I haſten
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5078:15"/>now to the ſecond part of our text,
<note place="margin">Theſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of the Text, to wit, the reaſon of the want.</note> to examine the reaſon of this want. <hi>(For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Philiſtines ſaid, leſt they make them wordes or ſpeares.)</hi> Theſe words do teach vs to know that the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Iſraelites want was the deepe pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cy of the ſubtile Philiſtines: who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing deſirous ſtill to keepe Iſrael in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ruitude, craftely inuented this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe,
<note place="margin">Pollicy of the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines.</note> to take their Smiths wholly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom them, to this end and purpoſe, that the Hebrewes might haue no heart to riſe vp in rebellion againſt them, or no hope of preuailing of they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d, being left deſtitute of weapons, either to defend themſelues, or to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their aduerſaries, this was a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous drift.</p>
            <p>Theſe craftie vncircumciſed Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines dealt with Gods people, as common robbers with vs deale, with true men and honeſt trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers: whome they firſt ſpoyle of their weapons, and afterwarde bind them; ſo theſe Philiſtines that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5078:16"/>they may keepe the Iſraelites fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> bound in the cords of their tyranny they do therefore take order that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may haue no warlike weapons whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with to helpe themſelues.</p>
            <p>This craft they learned of the ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Serpent,
<note place="margin">Sathan author of this pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy.</note> the father of all lies and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, who hath taught the Philiſtine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of our time the like craft in ſpiritua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> things, as he had inſpired into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Philiſtines of old for furtherance o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their worldly matters. For our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and Romiſh Philiſtines hauin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> enthralled vnder the heauy yoke o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their helliſh idolatry and hereſies th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> greateſt part of Europe,
<note place="margin">Popiſh po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy.</note> to the en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they may continue this iron yok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> holding in it kings, nations and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: therefore haue taken away th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lords Smiths, skilfull and godly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors: yea, not ſuffering the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> people his Chriſtian Iſrael (ſo much as they may) to haue that ſword o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſpirit, the word of God in thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hands, or haue in their mother toung<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:5078:16"/>without perill.</p>
            <p>Our owne and the French ſtories <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ford vs examples of their bloudy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd cruell counſels and practiſes in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his kind, reporting of ſome put to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ath and burned, becauſe they haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ene conuicted to haue had but a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hapter of the Bible, or a portion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Goſpell tranſlated in the vulgar <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nguage. I haue heard honeſt Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>emen which haue trauelled into <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> and thoſe parts neere Rome to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irme at their returne vpon good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nowledge, that not onely no Bible, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut not any other Proteſtant booke <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>which might giue any light vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uth againſt Popiſh errors) was to be found in the Italian tongue through all the Stationers and Book-ſellers ſhops there.</p>
            <p>This is the vniuerſall policy of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>opiſh Prelacy in all places (where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey can preuaile) to depriue the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all meanes to eſcape the ſlaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and tyrannicall butchery of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5078:17"/>for this purpoſe keeping from them by fire and ſword, both the weapon of the Scriptures, and ſuch wiſe and expert Smiths as might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them how to handle their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, herein lending their hand and helpe to Sathan (though with no ſuch direct intention) to ſtrengthen his power and increaſe his dominion, which by no way is more eſtabliſhed and enlarged, then by driuing out ſuch Smiths from vs, and denying that two edged ſword to vs.</p>
            <p>To deſcend from whole countries vnto particular perſons. When Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than would draw any backe into his ſnares who haue eſcaped them, or hold thoſe faſt which yet are entang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in his bands, is not this his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natie policy to perſwade tempted and troubled ſoules, that it bootes them not to reade or to heare,
<note place="margin">An ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Tempter.</note> and that it is in vaine for them to pray, for God will not heare ſuch ſinners, or elſe ſuch ſinners cannot pray to God? He
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5078:17"/>knowes full well how eaſie the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y will bee for him, if once hee may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aine this at our hands, that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome willing to caſt away our wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons: for then as naked and vnarmed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en, ſo we may be ouercome by him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ithout any ſtroake ſtriking. No <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orldly enemie feares the edge of a materiall ſword, ſo much as Sathan <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eareth the force of feruent prayer: which preuaileth much with that God, whoſe power alone is Sathans curbe and bane: Therefore hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolues that he hath more then halfe won the field, if he may winne this to make thee giue ouer praying to God in the mediation of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now ſithence we heare what poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies olde and new Philiſtines vſe for vpholding of their kingdomes, and whence they learne it, what remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth but this: that we be admoniſhed not onely to beware of them, leſt we be circumuented: But furthermore,
<note place="margin">Chriſtian pollicy.</note> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe ſuch policie to good purpoſes, as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:5078:18"/>they turne and employ vnto euill and miſchieuous ends.
<note place="margin">Children of the light ſhould be wiſe in their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Luke 16.</note> Our gouernours do imitate the deuiſe of the old Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines in the affaires of the common wealth: for there is order taken by acts of Parliament, that ſuch Papiſts as be knowne Recuſants, conuicted to be ſuch, refuſing the oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, ſhall be ſtript of all their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour (ſauing for neceſſary defence of their perſons) that if any ciuill or forraine warres ſhould ariſe, they might lacke meanes to hurt and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy their king and country, to which it is ſo well knowne, that they are ſo ill affected, like vipers, which come into the world with the death of their damme: Alſo here at home, if a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell or fray be likely to happen, the firſt care of our rulers and officers is this, to take from them their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons.</p>
            <p>Let vs imitate this policy alſo in our ſoule dangers, againſt the enemies thereof, to diſpoyle and rob them of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5078:18"/>ſuch weapons wherewith they vſe to fight againſt our ſoules. And ſeeing the luſt of honour and promotion is the weapon whereby Sathan fighteth againſt the ambitious, and againſt the couetous and letcherous, with the luſt of money and pleaſure; againſt the intemperate and proud, the malicious and enuious, with the concupiſcence of delights, prayſes and reuenge: Let it be our wiſedome to keepe, or (if he haue got hold of them) to wreſt theſe baites and inſtruments out of Sathans hands, that he may not therewith ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due vs to his will, and ouerthrow vs with deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, whoſoeuer haue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore giuen their members as wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons to ſinne to commit iniquity, let him now contrariwiſe giue his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers as weapons to righteouſneſſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to holineſſe.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, concerning you <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths,</hi> who haue hot worke in hand, which cauſeth dryneſſe, and this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendreth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5078:19"/>want of liquor to moyſten, and this breeds thirſt, and thirſt, not moderated, drawes on drunkenneſſe, and drunkenneſſe whets choler and wrath, and this kindles contention, and this puls on words, words beget blowes, blowes wounds, whereof ſometimes followeth death of body, and danger of ſoule (being in feare of being depriued of both parts of your ſelfe in one day, nay, in one houre:) let me therefore beſeech you to be ſober, to drinke for ſtrength, not for exceſſe, to liue temperatly at home with your wife and children: ſo ſhall ye withhold from Sathan a perilous weapon, wherewith (if ye ſhould put it into his hand) he will be able to cut the very throat of your ſoule vnto your eternall perdition. Let this ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice concerning the ſecond part of this text. Nowe to the third and laſt.</p>
            <p>The third thing obſerued in our text,
<note place="margin">The third part of the Text.</note> doth concerne the effects which
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:5078:19"/>did follow the peſtilent policy of the Philiſtines, in taking Smiths from the Hebrews. Theſe effectes do belong to the time of warre or of peace. In the time of warre they had neither ſword nor ſpeare, a ſore defect: for it gaue power and liberty to the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous, and tyrannous Philiſtines, a great deale more eaſily, not onely to keepe vnder the Iſraelites, but to kill them alſo: euen to take away their liues when they liſted, as they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore taken away their liberty. We may very well by our ſelues iudge how miſerable this caſe was, if we will but a little imagine it to be our owne caſe.</p>
            <p>Though we be now at peace with all our neighbour countries; yet doe but ſuppoſe that we wanted ſpeare, ſhield and ſword, bow and bill, guns, and all other military furniture offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue and defenſiue, is it not more then probable, and likely that we could not be in this peace foure and twenty
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:5078:20"/>dayes to an end: but that one or other which now holds league of peace with vs, more to ſerue their owne turne then for any loue to vs, would take the oportunity, eſpecially ſuch as hold their hands off, becauſe they are too weake for vs: lacking not will but might to deſtroy this noble king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and be glad to make a ſpoyle of our riches, and a maſſaker of our perſons.</p>
            <p>And touching the other euill effect enſuing the want of Smiths, if it were ſo with vs, that for our axes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we hew our wood, or mattocks wherewith we digge our ground, our ſhares wherewith we plough our fields, and our hookes wherewith we weed our corne, we ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to trauell ſo farre as Scotland, or Wales, or Holland to whet them when they were blunt and vnfit for vſe; might we not thinke this (and that worthily) to be a very great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie?</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:5078:20"/>
            <p>This was the very caſe of the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, whoſe land was much like in compaſſe (as appeares by the maps) to this our Realme of England. There being then neither in towne nor city a Smith to be had, it muſt needs be that ſuch as dwelt in ſome part of the country, were driuen to trauell very far when they had need but to whet a toole: for they were faine to go to the Philiſtines for it, who had gotten all their Smiths into their coaſts. From hence there is iuſt occaſion of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to ſay ſomething of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie of Black-ſmiths, as before we ſpake of their worth, ancientneſſe, and needfulneſſe.
<note place="margin">Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of Smiths in peace.</note> For the times of peace what vſe and benefit they are to vs it is more manifeſt then I neede to ſay much: for who is ignorant that this trade doth helpe to maintaine huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, by which euen the King is maintained. The life both of prince and ſubiect is preſerued by the fruits of the ground, and theſe cannot be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5078:21"/>attained without the aid of the Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith, who ſhapeth and ſharpens the inſtruments by which the ground is manured.</p>
            <p>What ſhall I tell you, that neither could you haue Cities to dwell in, nor Churches to ſerue God in, nor ſhips to tranſport, and import com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities by, were it not for Smiths, who make thoſe inſtruments, by which great Fabricks are both made and maintained? Neither can we in the night lye ſafe in our beds, for feare of theeues, if the Smiths daughter be not before their hands. Nor trauaile in the day ſecurely for robbers, were we not armed with weapons of their framing. And touching the vſe of them in warre; becauſe euery man doth ſufficiently vnderſtand, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our harneſſe can be at the firſt faſhioned,
<note place="margin">For war.</note> nor afterward burniſhed, and made fit for vſe, but by their hands; therefore I am determined to ſpend, no more time in a thing ſo
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5078:21"/>plaine.</p>
            <p>I will addreſſe my ſelfe now,
<note place="margin">Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hotation to men of all callings to behaue themſelues religiouſly and iuſtly in them.</note> that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue ſhewed you the dignity, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quity, neceſſity, and commodiry of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s your calling, to inſtruct you how t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cary your ſelues worthy ſo good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d commendable a vocation. For the which purpoſe, there are two things ſereof you haue ſpeciall need, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt take ſpeciall care of; the one is, that you walke in your calling religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſly: the other, that you behaue your ſelues iuſtly therein.</p>
            <p>But this I would haue noted, that what I ſpeake to you Black-ſmiths, for exhortation to carry your ſelues vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly and religiouſly in your cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: the ſame I alſo ſpeake to all ſere preſent, of what art or function ſoeuer they be. Hearken then, I pray you, and conſider, that to a religious walking in your calling, there be theſe fiue things very requiſite. Firſt, ſound and diſtinct knowledge. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, true faith. Thirdly, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5078:22"/>hope. Fourthly, feruent prayer. And laſtly, humble thankfulneſſe, Of each of theſe a little, and but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle.</p>
            <p>To begin with knowledge,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> which is the beginning of euery good action.
<note place="margin">Knowledg.</note> That which the Apoſtle ſpeakes of meates, and marriages, that they muſt be ſanctified by the word. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.4, or elſe the vſe of them cannot be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and good vnto vs, the very ſame is to be affirmed concerning all trades and functions, that ye cannot vſe them with a good conſcience, vnleſſe your minds be firſt informed, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned by the word to know their lawfulneſſe, and directed by the ſame word to the right vſe of them. Ignorance which is the mother of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in opinion, is alſo the mother of ſinne in action: men do erre both in iudgement,
<note place="margin">Mat. 22.29. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Faith. Heb. 11.</note> and practiſe, becauſe they know not the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>But what vſe is there for faith (will you ſay) toward the religious perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5078:22"/>of our manuary workes? Yes very great: For it is written, that <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith we cannot pleaſe God:</hi> neither we, nor our workes can pleaſe God, vnleſſe they become acceptable vnto him through faith. Two actions of faith there be needfull to him, that will do the duties of his calling in a religious ſort, acceptable to God.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">1. Action of faith.</note> to apprehend the promiſe of forgiueneſſe of ſinnes by Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing that God is reconciled to our perſons by the bloud of that imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate Lambe: for as a gift can neuer be welcome vnto vs,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
               </label> when we diſlike the giuer: ſo God is neuer well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with any thing that we do, till he be pleaſed with vs.</p>
            <p>The ſecond office of faith,
<note place="margin">2. Action of faith.</note> is to aſſure our hearts, that our calling is warrantable, that we may do the workes thereof with a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and that through pardon of the wants, and faults that ſticke to them, (as they come from vs) they are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5078:23"/>of God through that media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, by whom we know our ſelues to be accepted. If any of you haue gotten this faith, you may be bold and well perſwaded, that the meaneſt worke you do in your calling, euen to the wiping of a ſhooe, and ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of a houſe, &amp; driuing in a horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naile, is gratious vnto that God, who doth euer more reſpect the manner, then the matter of our workes.
<note place="margin">3. Hope.</note> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour therefore in faith, and labour al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vnder hope; for ſeeing God hath made a couenant with you to be your God, and this couenant containeth in it things earthly belonging to this life, as well as ſpirituall things belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to the life to come; it is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your part, and duty, to do euery worke of your calling with a ſure ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, and hope for a bleſſing from God.</p>
            <p>Howbeit ſeeing the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment enioynes ſuch as will haue,
<note place="margin">4. Prayer.</note> and find, any bleſſing from God, that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:5078:23"/>they muſt firſt aske, and ſeeke it; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is your duty to giue all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, as to ioyne faith to your knowledge, and hope to your faith: ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o adde prayer to your hope.
<note place="margin">Iam. 1.16.</note> Euery good gift and perfect giuing comes from aboue: and therefore you muſt begin your worke with prayer.
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.4.</note> All the creatures of God, and all the lawfull workes of men are ſanctified by prayer; therefore either muſt god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prayer go before euery lawfull du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or elſe it will be polluted, and profained, and turned into ſinne to vs. Moreouer, we cannot ſtirre a fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger without God, <hi>in whom we liue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 17.</note> 
               <hi>moue, and haue our being,</hi> and as all our ſtrength to worke is from him, ſo all ſucceſſe of our work comes from him alſo, (for the builder labours but in vaine, except God build the houſe) wherefore as you deſire to ſee the fruit of your labour, and that it ſhould go well with you, in any wiſe ſee, and looke to it, that you call your familie
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:5078:24"/>together in the beginning of the day, before you begin your work, make an entrance by praier, deſiring your good God to ſtrengthen, direct, and to proſper your handy worke, but this is not all, as you begin the day with God, ſo if you do well you muſt end it with God. Humble thankſgiuing muſt alwaies accompany harty pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for he that commanded, ſaying, <hi>Pray continually,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 1.18.19.</note> did alſo charge vs in al things to giue thanks. Againe, if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our worke we ſhall pray for a helpe and a bleſſing, and after our worke is proſpered and ended, ſhould not returne thanks to God, this would witneſſe againſt vs that we ſought rather our owne profit then Gods praiſe: beſides, for as much as thankfulneſſe is a ſacrifice of ſweet ſmelling ſauour to God,
<note place="margin">Heb. 13.</note> better liked then a bullocke with hornes, and hooues, and is all the rent, charge, and homage, exacted of vs, for all the good things which we hold of God:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:5078:24"/>therefore let euery one be as willing and forward to offer vp thankſgiuing before he ſleepe, as he was to ſend vp prayers before his worke: ſo ſhall God be rightly glorified, and you ſoundly comforted in all that you put your hand vnto;
<note place="margin">2. Iuſtly,</note> eſpecially if your care be as to walke religiouſly, ſo to deale iuſtly in your vocations, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the power of your piety towards God, by the fruits of righteouſneſſe towards men, to which end you haue need of two graces principally, Loue, and Integrity.</p>
            <p>Loue will cauſe you not to ſeeke ſo much your owne,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <note place="margin">Loue.</note> as the profit and good of others. So it is teſtified of Loue, that it doth not ſeeke it owne things. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. they that labour in their callings for no other ende but that they and others may liue, they ſhew forth not Chriſtian, but ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loue, ſuch as may be found in Turks, Iewes, Pagans and Heathen, who by the light of nature are ſtirred vp to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:5078:25"/>take care for themſelues and their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.6.7.</note> to prouide food for the belly, and cloth for the backe: yea, the very brute beaſts by the inſtinct of nature are moued to ſeeke out for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and their yong ones, that they may be able to liue without periſhing for want of meate. Therefore as our Sauiour Chriſt ſaid vnto them that would loue none, but they that loued them; and would do good to none, but to them that do good to them againe, what a ſingular thing do ye? do not euen the publicanes and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners the ſame? So I ſay to theſe that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in their calling, diligently and conſtantly: yet, for their liuing ſake onely, not for the common good of that ſociety wherein they liue, what ſingular thing do ye? Do not the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans; nay, the very brute beaſts the ſame? Hearken therefore to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile of the Apoſtle, willing vs to do all things in loue, which will make vs to reſpect our neighbour as well as
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5078:25"/>our ſelues, and in ſeruing our ſelues to ſerue others.</p>
            <p>The next vertue required to your iuſt walking in your callings,
<note place="margin">Integrity.</note> it is Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, that you do vnto euery one that which is right, making your ware ſubſtantiall, and your price e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, that you may giue as good as you take, auoyding all wrong, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, and oppreſſion. To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, I beſeech you,
<note place="margin">Reaſons to perſwade louing and iuſt dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</note> to conſider of theſe few reaſons, why you ought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this ſort to cary your ſelues in your vocations.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> if you do not deale louing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and vprightly, it will coſt you no leſſe then the loſſe both of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and kingdome: for it is written, that <hi>vnrighteous perſons ſhall not inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite the hingdome of heauen.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9. Therefore looke to it, for as ſure as God ſpake this,
<note place="margin">Non tollitur peceatum, niſi restitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur rable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> ſo ſure it is they ſhall neuer be ſaued, that deale deciptful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, except they repent, and reſtore if they be able. Againe, if you deale ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5078:26"/>and deceiptfully with your neighbours vttering bad ware in ſtead of good, or bad and good to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether (as if all were good) or good ware onely at too high a rate, you ſhall giue teſtimony to the world, and to your ſelues that you are his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who is the father of lyes.</p>
            <p>We vſe to terrifie our children from lying with this argument,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they that lye are the diuels chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and in the 13 of the <hi>Acts, Paul</hi> doth conclude <hi>Elymas</hi> to be the child of the diuell, becauſe he was full of ſubtilty: doth it not then ſtand you vpon as you would not be counted the children of ſuch a father, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre a deceiptfull lying tongue, and falſe weights, both which are as abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable to God, as they be pleaſing to ſathan.</p>
            <p>Adde hereunto that you cannot deceiue,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and wrong others in your dealings, but that you much more deceiue and wrong your ſelues, for
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:5078:26"/>by vncharitable and vnrighteous practiſe in your callings, you giue a deepe wound. Firſt, to your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Secondly, to your credit. And thirdly to your ſtate. Your conſcience by your ſin takes a greater gaſh then any ſword can giue vnto your fleſh, and it cannot but be a great bleamiſh to your reputation and names, when you gaine the report of vnhoneſt, and vnfaithfull dealers, the very fame and noiſe whereof will be as a ſharpe and ſtrong ſcourge, to driue away from you all your cuſtomers.</p>
            <p>Thinke vpon theſe things ſeriouſly when you are tempted to any falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and iniury, &amp; do but aske your ſelfe, at that time, when you are about to offer it vnto others, whether ye could be pleaſed to haue it done to your ſelues, and if your conſcience tell you, that you your ſelues would not be ill dealt withall; then take heed how you offer ill meaſure to others. For this is the law, and the Prophets,
<note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:5078:27"/>to do to others as we would be done to, I am ſure if a ſmith, Pewterer, or Ioyner, if he haue to do with a Tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, he will looke to haue all his cloth put into his garment, or elſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to him that which is too much. Let the Smith and the Cutler do like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe vnto others: and the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if your ware ſhould not be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall; it may proue not onely hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to ſuch as vſe it, but turne to the harme and vndoing alſo of many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as if a ſword haue not a ſtrong backe it may breake, and be the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of an army, if a ſtrake be not firme it may ouerturne the wagon, and the paſſengers, as is often ſeene by lamentable experience, if a plough be not ſharpe it will make no furrow in the earth.</p>
            <p>Finally,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> that we may draw to an end, among innumerable reaſons which may preuaile to hold you in a louing and vpright courſe one toward another, be ye alwaies mindfull of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:5078:27"/>your death, and of the laſt iudgment. For would you ſeriouſly thinke vpon this, and beleeue that you are mortall, brittle, and glaſſy creatures, and of a daies continuance, like to the ſmoake that vaniſheth, like to the weauers ſhuttle, and to the Eagles, that paſſe &amp; flie away ſwiftly, haſtening to your graues, as the day to an end, hauing death euer at your elbow, ready as a ſergeant, or baylife to arreſt you:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> and withall ponder this, that being dead, you muſt come before that al-ſeeing, ſeuere, and mighty Iudge: whoſe knowledge you cannot deceiue, whoſe power you cannot auoid, whoſe iuſtice you cannot eſcape, and whoſe wrath you are neuer able to abide. Theſe meditations being imprinted in your hearts, would moue and bow them (were they as hard as flint) to relent for your miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dealing paſt, laying hold on Gods mercies in Chriſt for pardon, and conſcionably to looke to your ſteppes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5078:28"/>in time to come, and ſurely if ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> and the Euangeliſt <hi>Timothy</hi> did ſet before their eyes the terrour of that day,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10. 2. Tim. 4.1.2.</note> and the comming of that dreadfull iudge that they might hold themſelues the better to the duties of their callings, let not other men thinke if they neglect ſuch meditations, that they ſhall well and worthily diſcharg their workes? That ancient father <hi>Hierome</hi> profeſſed of himſelfe that whether he were at home, or abroad, in worke, or recreation, eating, drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, walking, talking, ſleeping, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thought ſtill he heard a trumpet ſound, &amp; a voice ſaying vnto him, <hi>ariſe from the dead and come to iudgement.</hi> Bleſſed are they that are thus watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, alwaies thinking vpon their own ends, and the worlds end, that when the Bridgrome commeth either, to euery man particularly by death, or to all generally by iudgement, he may find vs all ready &amp; prepared, with the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:5078:28"/>good ſeruant in the Goſpell, hauing our loynes girt, and our lampes bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that we may enter with him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his ioyes, which God grant euen for Chriſt Ieſus ſake, to whom with the Father, and the holy Spirit, be all praiſe, and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing now and for euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
